A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of the Vice President of Administration, Office Files of Arthur D. Trottenberg FA669
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Program Activity, 1958-1979; 1968-1977; VII
  - Financial Reviews of Grantees
    - Esola, Ronald, 1971 (Box 40, Folder 408)
    - Esola, Ronald, 1972 (Box 40, Folder 409)
    - Masone Jr., Nunzio, 1972 (Box 40, Folder 410)
    - Wolf, Thomas, Leonard Spilka, and Charles Stewart, 1972 (Box 40, Folder 411)
    - Stewart, Charles, 1973 (Box 41, Folder 412)
    - Cavanaugh, Harry and Lee Harris, 1973-1974 (Box 41, Folder 413)
    - Masone Jr., Nunzio and Ronald Esola, 1973 February-June (Box 41, Folder 414)
    - Masone Jr., Nunzio and Ronald Esola, 1973 July-December (Box 41, Folder 415)
    - Masone Jr., Nunzio and Ronald Esola, 1974 (Box 41, Folder 416)
    - Wolf, Thomas, Leonard Spilka, and Ronald Walker, 1973-1975 (Box 41, Folder 417)
    - Cavanaugh, Harry, 1974-1975 (Box 41, Folder 418)
    - Doran, John, 1974 (Box 41, Folder 419)
    - Doran, John, 1975 (Box 41, Folder 420)
- Self Study, 1955-1979; 1968-1973; VIII
  Items within each folder are arranged chronologically, maintaining original order.
  Series VIII, Self Study, is housed in three archival boxes. The series consists of various task forces and other studies the Foundation conducted on itself. Studies cover topics such as financial accounting, overseas compensation, FAP resource allocation, and telecommunications. The series consists of memoranda, correspondence, reports, questionnaires, newspaper articles, charts, and notes.
  Self Study The Self Study series contains a number of self studies and task forces that the Foundation conducted in order to learn more about itself and how it runs in order to improve Foundation policies and procedures. There are a few studies on overseas offices (Overseas Development Self Study, Overseas Compensation Study, and Overseas Task Force) that can be used in conjunction with the Overseas series in order to round out the researchers knowledge of the overseas component of the Foundation's administration. There are a number of other studies dealing with the size of the Foundation in terms of assets and expenditures. For instance, Paul Strasburg's paper on the size of Foundation argues breaking the Foundation into smaller divisions, basing his argument on the various effects the action would cause for the public. Trottenberg, ever concerned with the Foundation's need for retrenchment, disagreed with Strasburg's proposal, arguing that decentralizing the Foundation would increase its general management costs. Other studies also deal with the issue of the Foundation's costs, such as the Cost Comparison Study. Some studies deal less directly with how the Foundation is run, and more on how it can expand its program areas. For instance, the Telecommunications Task Force aimed to study the impact of telecommunications, beyond just television, on society, in order to assess how the Foundation could be involved in the field.
  - Self Study Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 42, Folder 421)
  - Task Force on Financial Accounting, 1971 (Box 42, Folder 422)
  - Ford Foundation Size, 1955-1973 (Box 42, Folder 423)
  - Cost Comparison Study, 1972-1973 (Box 42, Folder 424)
  - Joint Cost Study, 1973-1979 (Box 42, Folder 425)
  - Goals and Objectives for Administration, 1960-1967 (Box 42, Folder 426)
  - The People at Ford, 1972 (Box 42, Folder 427)
  - Overseas Development Self Study, 1966 (Box 43, Folder 428)
  - Overseas Development Self Study, 1966-1967 (Box 43, Folder 429)
  - Overseas Questionnaire and Results, 1968 (Box 43, Folder 430)
  - Overseas Compensation Study, 1968-1969 March (Box 43, Folder 431)
  - Overseas Compensation Study, 1969 April-August (Box 43, Folder 432)
  - Overseas Compensation Study, 1969 September-November (Box 43, Folder 433)
  - Overseas Task Force, 1972-1974 (Box 43, Folder 434)
  - FAP, Resource Allocation Study, 1970 (Box 43, Folder 435)
  - FAP, Resource Allocation Study, 1971 January-April (Box 44, Folder 436)
  - FAP, Resource Allocation Study, 1971 May-August (Box 44, Folder 437)
  - Telecommunications Task Force, 1972-1973 (Box 44, Folder 438)
- Subject Files, 1949-1979; 1968-1977; IX
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic, and items within each folder are arranged chronologically, maintaining original order.
  Series IX, Subject Files, is housed in thirteen archival boxes. The series consists of a number of topical subject files. Some of the most significant and widely-covered topics include affirmative action, the agricultural institutes dependent upon Foundation support, the Employment Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (ERISA), retrenchment of Foundation expenses, and the Tax Reform Act of 1969. The series consists of memoranda, correspondence, telegrams, reports, policy papers, speeches/statements, questionnaires, newspaper articles, charts, notes, photographs, and blueprints.
  Subject Files The Subject Files series contains the topical subject files, documenting many of the activities and issues with which the Foundation was involved during Trottenberg's time. The topics range from work with Magnum Films to create a documentary of the Foundation's current building at the time of its construction in 1967, to work with a number of grantees, such as Yale University and their Pay As You Earn (PAYE) student loans plan. The series also contains information on housing for then-president, McGeorge Bundy, and Board of Trustees member, Julius A. Stratton. The folders associated with this topic (box 46, folders 454-458) are restricted in their accessibility by researchers. Researchers should consult the Foundation's archivist prior to reviewing the material within those folders. Some of the most significant and well-documented topics in the series include organizations dependent on Foundation support (particularly several agricultural institutes), the Tax Reform Act of 1969, and the Employment Retirement Income Security Act of 1974, retrenchment of foundation expenses, and affirmative action.
  Dependent Organizations: The Ford Foundation gives financial support to many organizations, but some of these receive so much support that they are deemed to be largely, if not wholly, dependent upon the Foundation. This series documents a number of organizations that fall into this category, such as the Institute of International Education (IIE). Relying on the Foundation for general support, IIE is an organization that administers international education and technical assistance programs, and it has worked with many of the Foundation's individual grant projects all over the world. For instance, IIE has worked with several agricultural institutes that are also dependent upon Foundation support. The Foundation helped to establish several agricultural institutes, such as the International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) in the Philippines. IRRI was established in 1960 order to accelerate and improve the development of rice varieties and their production techniques. Other, agricultural research and training centers include International Institute of Tropical Agriculture in Nigeria, Centro Internacional de Agricultura Tropical in Colombia, and Centro Internacional de Mejoramiento de Maiz Y Trigo in Mexico.
  Tax Reform Act of 1969: The Tax Reform Act of 1969, signed into law by President Nixon on December 30, 1969, provides an extensive legal framework requiring philanthropic foundations to be more publicly accountable for their work. For the most part, the Foundation considered the new law to be a positive change, but it would still demand that the Foundation adjust their programs and procedures in order to comply with the new regulations. For instance, in an effort to prevent foundations from being misused in such a way that they financially benefit their founders, the Act set requirements such as a minimum payout of six percent of assets or of full next investment income (whichever is higher). Other provisions include a new kind of "expenditure responsibility" over grants, demanding that foundations perform certain monitoring duties that previously had been the responsibility of the Internal Revenue Service, and a four percent excise tax on the net investment income of foundations. The series documents the Foundation's reactions to the Tax Reform Act of 1969 as well as the process through which the Foundation altered its programs and procedures in order to comply with the Act and its related amendments. For basic background information about the legislation's provisions and the Foundation's reactions, the researcher may want to refer to the Ford Foundation Annual Report 1969.
  Employment Retirement Income Security Act of 1974: Another law that affected the Foundation during Trottenberg's time was the Employment Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (ERISA). With the enactment of ERISA, Congress established a new regulatory framework for employee benefit plans, including more detailed requirements relating to fiduciary responsibility. The series documents the Foundation's process of understanding the Act and putting it to work with its own benefits plans, particularly its retirement and thrift plans.
  Retrenchment: One of the major issues with which Trottenberg dealt during his tenure at the Foundation was the retrenchment program. In fact, in a memorandum to the staff announcing Trottenberg's retirement from the Foundation, then-president, Franklin Thomas, paid particular attention to Trottenberg's diligence in dealing with the difficulties stemming from the Foundation's retrenchment period.
  The latter half of the 1970s was marked by a period of severe reduction of the Foundation's general management costs and program budgets. Financial reductions first became a necessity in 1967 and 1971 in order to preserve the Foundation's longevity. However, the Foundation's projections at those times were too hopeful, and combined with the bad economies of 1973 and 1974, the Foundation needed to undergo even larger reductions in order to remain a stable institution. Thus, at the December 1974 meeting of the Board of Trustees, a new target for annual spending was set at $100 million, requiring a 50% budget cut. Budget cuts were implemented across all areas of Foundation spending – from a reduced size and decrease in the number of grants to the termination of employees. Trottenberg recommended setting up an appropriation from the Foundation's General Funds to create a Retrenchment Fund. First recommended in 1975 and expected to last as long as 1979, the Retrenchment Fund began as $500,000 set aside by the Foundation to cover costs associated with the retrenchment program. For instance, the IBM Computerized Energy Conservation Power Management System was utilized to conserve energy and in turn, it reduced operating costs of the Foundation's building. Since the system helped to cut costs, its installation was charged to the Retrenchment Fund.
  The series documents the retrenchment program from setting up the Retrenchment Fund to how the financial reductions would affect all aspects of the Foundation, such as employees and field offices.
  Affirmative Action: As affirmative action for women and minorities became an important social movement in the 1970s, Trottenberg paid particular attention. He emphasized hiring women and minorities as Foundation employees, as well as hiring minority consultants. The concern for affirmative action was such that a subcommittee of the Affirmative Action Committee, chaired by William Gormbley, was created in order to study the possibility of revitalizing the Training Associate Program in an attempt to improve the Foundation's affirmative action program. The affirmative action folders in the Subject Files series include Trottenberg's background research on the affirmative action policies of other institutions, and document creating and abiding by affirmative action policies within the Foundation.
  Though the bulk of materials on this subject are found in the Subject Files series, this issue was clearly important to Trottenberg, as his emphasis on it is evident throughout the entire collection. For instance, in the Financial series, a folder on consulting firm Lucas, Tucker, and Company contains a study by Bert Mitchell, and strongly encouraged by Trottenberg, on the presence of black CPAs in the accounting profession. Evidence of Trottenberg's concern for affirmative action is also present in such series as Administration and Operations and Memoranda and Correspondence.
  - Administrative Conference, 1971-1972 (Box 44, Folder 439)
  - Affirmative Action – General Material and Clippings, 1972-1975 (Box 44, Folder 440)
  - Affirmative Action – General Material and Clippings, 1970-1972 (Box 44, Folder 441)
  - Affirmative Action – General Material and Clippings, 1971-1973 (Box 44, Folder 442)
  - Affirmative Action – General Material and Clippings, 1970-1972 (Box 44, Folder 443)
  - Affirmative Action – General Material and Clippings, 1970 (Box 45, Folder 444)
  - Affirmative Action – Role of Women at Ford Foundation, 1971 January-March (Box 45, Folder 445)
  - Affirmative Action – Role of Women at Ford Foundation, 1971 May-1972 (Box 45, Folder 446)
  - Affirmative Action – Drake-Beam Study, 1970 (Box 45, Folder 447)
  - Affirmative Action – Drake-Beam Study, 1971 January (Box 45, Folder 448)
  - Affirmative Action – Drake-Beam Study, 1971 February-1973 (Box 45, Folder 449)
  - Affirmative Action – Towers, Perrin, Forster & Crosby, 1972-1973 (Box 45, Folder 450)
  - Affirmative Action – Ulric Hayes and Minority Personnel, 1967-1972 (Box 45, Folder 451)
  - Affirmative Action – Job Opportunities, 1972-1975 (Box 45, Folder 452)
  - American Historical Association, 1965-1970 (Box 46, Folder 453)
  - Apartment – Bundy, McGeorge, 1966-1976 (Box 46, Folder 454)
  - Apartment – Bundy, McGeorge, 1966-1967 (Box 46, Folder 455)
  - Apartment – Stratton, Julius A., 1966-1971 (Box 46, Folder 456)
  - Apartment – Stratton, Julius A., 1966-1971 (Box 46, Folder 457)
  - Apartment – Stratton, Julius A., 1966 (Box 46, Folder 458)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, 1970-1972 (Box 46, Folder 459)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, 1973-1976 (Box 47, Folder 460)
  - Bylaws of Ford Foundation, 1949-1964 (Box 47, Folder 461)
  - Center for War and Peace Studies, 1968 (Box 47, Folder 462)
  - Community Development Conference, 1971 (Box 47, Folder 463)
  - Congress of Racial Equality, 1968-1969 (Box 47, Folder 464)
  - Council on Foundations, 1971-1973 (Box 47, Folder 465)
  - Dependent Organizations, general, 1968-1971 (Box 47, Folder 466)
  - Dependent Organizations – Educational Facilities Lab. Inc., 1976 (Box 47, Folder 467)
  - Dependent Organizations – International Food Policy Research Institute, 1975-1976 (Box 47, Folder 468)
  - Dependent Organizations – Institute of International Education, 1969-1970 (Box 47, Folder 469)
  - Dependent Organizations – Institute of International Education, 1971-1974 (Box 47, Folder 470)
  - Dependent Organizations – Institute of International Education, 1975-1979 (Box 47, Folder 471)
  - Dependent Organizations – Agricultural Institutes, 1966-1968 (Box 48, Folder 472)
  - Dependent Organizations – Agricultural Institutes, 1969 January-February (Box 48, Folder 473)
  - Dependent Organizations – Agricultural Institutes, 1969 March-May (Box 48, Folder 474)
  - Dependent Organizations – Agricultural Institutes, 1969 June-December (Box 48, Folder 475)
  - Dependent Organizations – Agricultural Institutes, 1970-1971 (Box 48, Folder 476)
  - Dependent Organizations – Agricultural Institutes, 1972 (Box 48, Folder 477)
  - Dependent Organizations – Agricultural Institutes, 1973 (Box 48, Folder 478)
  - Dependent Organizations – Agricultural Institutes, 1974-1977 (Box 49, Folder 479)
  - Dependent Organizations – Agricultural Institutes, budgets - FY 1970, 1969 (Box 49, Folder 480)
  - Dependent Organizations – Agricultural Institutes, benefits, 1969 (Box 49, Folder 481)
  - Dependent Organizations – Consultative Group for International Agricultural Research, 1977 (Box 49, Folder 482)
  - Doane Agricultural Service, 1970 (Box 49, Folder 483)
  - Edison Institute, 1970 (Box 49, Folder 484)
  - Energy Policy Project, 1971-1974 (Box 49, Folder 485)
  - Employment Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (ERISA), 1973-1974 September (Box 49, Folder 486)
  - ERISA, 1974 October-December (Box 50, Folder 487)
  - ERISA, 1975 January-September (Box 50, Folder 488)
  - ERISA, 1975 October (Box 50, Folder 489)
  - ERISA, 1975 November (Box 50, Folder 490)
  - ERISA, 1975 December (Box 50, Folder 491)
  - ERISA, 1976-1977 (Box 50, Folder 492)
  - Ford Family Painting, 1973-1978 (Box 50, Folder 493)
  - Haile Selassie I University, 1969-1971 (Box 51, Folder 494)
  - Haile Selassie I University, 1972 January-May (Box 51, Folder 495)
  - Haile Selassie I University, 1972 July (Box 51, Folder 496)
  - Haile Selassie I University, 1972 August-December (Box 51, Folder 497)
  - Industry Position Papers, tabs 1-3, 1973 (Box 51, Folder 498)
  - Industry Position Papers, tabs 4-6, 1973 (Box 51, Folder 499)
  - Leadership Development Program, 1969-1973 (Box 51, Folder 500)
  - London School of Economics, 1966-1969 (Box 51, Folder 501)
  - Magnum Films, 1967-1969 (Box 52, Folder 502)
  - Metropolitan Applied Research Center, Inc., 1970 (Box 52, Folder 503)
  - New York City Schools, 1968 (Box 52, Folder 504)
  - Overseas Schools Advisory Council, 1971-1974 (Box 52, Folder 505)
  - Pan Am Heliport, 1967-1970 (Box 52, Folder 506)
  - Pay As You Earn (PAYE) Student Loans, 1969-1971 (Box 52, Folder 507)
  - Peterson Commission, 1969-1970 (Box 52, Folder 508)
  - Rand Corporation, 1969-1970 (Box 52, Folder 509)
  - Retrenchment, general, 1974 (Box 52, Folder 510)
  - Retrenchment, general, 1975 January-February (Box 52, Folder 511)
  - Retrenchment, general, 1975 March-1979 (Box 52, Folder 512)
  - Retrenchment – Retrenchment Fund, 1975-1979 (Box 53, Folder 513)
  - Retrenchment – Field Offices, 1975-1978 (Box 53, Folder 514)
  - Retrenchment – Terminations, 1975-1979 (Box 53, Folder 515)
  - Retrenchment – Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 53, Folder 516)
  - Salzburg Seminar in American Studies, 1968-1972 (Box 53, Folder 517)
  - Search Committee for President (of Ford Foundation), 1973-1979 (Box 53, Folder 518)
  - Soul and Latin Theater, Inc., 1970 (Box 53, Folder 519)
  - Taconic Foundation, 1969 (Box 53, Folder 520)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969, general, 1968-1969 May (Box 53, Folder 521)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969, general, 1969 June-August (Box 53, Folder 522)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969, general, 1969 September-December (Box 53, Folder 523)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969, general, 1970 January (Box 54, Folder 524)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969, general, 1970 February-March (Box 54, Folder 525)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969, general, 1970 April-November (Box 54, Folder 526)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969, general, 1971-1972 (Box 54, Folder 527)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 – McGeorge Bundy, 1969-1970 (Box 54, Folder 528)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 – FAPs, 1969-1971 (Box 54, Folder 529)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 – House Ways and Means Committee, 1969 April-May (Box 54, Folder 530)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 – House Ways and Means Committee, 1969 June-August (Box 54, Folder 531)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 – Impact on Foundations, 1969-1970 (Box 55, Folder 532)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 – Statements of Initial Witnesses Appearing Before the Senate Finance Committee (Box 55, Folder 533)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 – Statements of Initial Witnesses Appearing Before the Senate Finance Committee (Box 55, Folder 534)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 – Hearing Held Before Committee on Finance (Box 55, Folder 535)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 – Congressman Patman, 1970-1974 (Box 55, Folder 536)
  - Television, 1966-1968 (Box 55, Folder 537)
  - Travel Program for Foreign Diplomats, 1969-1977 (Box 55, Folder 538)
  - United Fund of Greater NY, 1969 (Box 56, Folder 539)
  - United Fund of Greater NY, 1970-1971 (Box 56, Folder 540)
  - United Fund of Greater NY, 1972 (Box 56, Folder 541)
  - United Fund of Greater NY, 1973-1975 (Box 56, Folder 542)
  - United Nations International School, 1968-1976 (Box 56, Folder 543)
  - Winsor School, 1970 (Box 56, Folder 544)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, 1969 (Box 56, Folder 545)
  - Yale University, 1969-1971 (Box 56, Folder 546)
- Real Estate, 1966-1979; 1967-1976; X
  The General subseries contains general information on the Foundation's investments in real estate, as well as information on all real estate investments that fall outside of the U.N.D.C. The U.N.D.C subseries is the stronger of the two in this series. It contains material documenting the development of the U.N. area from the setting up of bylaws for the U.N.D.C. to information on some specific real estate investments such as the Beaux Arts Hotel. The series consists of memoranda, correspondence, reports, press releases, newspaper articles, notes, maps, and blueprints.
  Series X, Real Estate, is housed in five archival boxes, and is divided into two subseries: General and United Nations Development Corporation (U.N.D.C.). Items within the folders are arranged chronologically, maintaining original order.
  Real Estate The Real Estate series contains information on the Foundation's investments in real estate, particularly focusing on the United Nations Development Corporation (U.N.D.C.). In fact, the decision by the Board of Trustees to locate the current Foundation building in the vicinity of the United Nations was made with the express idea that the new building could then serve as a catalyst for developing and improving the entire area. Soon after the Foundation's building was built, the Board of Trustees Executive Committee began a real estate investment plan to acquire 28 properties located in a two block "core development area" spanning between 43rd and 45th Streets and 1st and 2nd Avenues. The initial work in setting up this real estate investment plan in the U.N. area predated Trottenberg, but he quickly became involved once his term at the Foundation began. In the May of 1968, just before Trottenberg joined the Foundation, the New York State Legislature passed a law that set the two block core development area aside as the United Nations Development District. The law also created the United Nations Development Corporation to develop the district or to make arrangements with private sponsors to develop it. The Foundation's involvement with and financial support for the U.N.D.C. was motivated by a desire to improve the area of the U.N. in order to serve public interest by demonstrating the possibility to effect dramatic, qualitative changes with a strong social purpose through cooperation of the public and private sectors.
  - General
    - Real Estate, general, 1970-1971 (Box 56, Folder 547)
    - Investment Reports, 1972 (Box 56, Folder 548)
    - Wilson Property, 1969-1975 (Box 56, Folder 549)
    - Financial Reports, 1973-1974 (Box 56, Folder 550)
    - Wholly-Owned Subsidiaries, 1976 (Box 56, Folder 551)
    - Portfolio Reviews, 1976 (Box 56, Folder 552)
    - Real Estate Strategy Paper, 1977 (Box 56, Folder 553)
  - United Nations Development Corporation (U.N.D.C.)
    - United Nations Development Corporation, general, 1966-1969 (Box 56, Folder 554)
    - U.N.D.C., general, 1970 (Box 57, Folder 555)
    - U.N.D.C., general, 1972 (Box 57, Folder 556)
    - U.N.D.C., general, 1973 January-June (Box 57, Folder 557)
    - U.N.D.C., general, 1973 August-December (Box 57, Folder 558)
    - U.N.D.C., general, 1974-1975 (Box 57, Folder 559)
    - Development of U.N. Area, 1966 (Box 57, Folder 560)
    - Development of U.N. Area, 1967 January-June (Box 57, Folder 561)
    - Development of U.N. Area, 1967 July-December (Box 57, Folder 562)